Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is דף י׳, Daf
Yud, מנחות Menachos 10. We're a little bit behind, we pick up
five lines down in the wide lines on ט׳ עמוד ב׳, Tes
Amud Beis, we're in the middle of the debate of רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish about what is the story
by a מנחה mincha if after you took the קמיצה, kmitza, the
hand-breath, some of the remainder of the שיריים shirayim went missing, where
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says that it's invalid, he learns that from
a special פסוק, passuk, even though by a comparable case by an
animal if you had some of the meat left everybody would agree
it's okay or some of the fat left but here he says
it's no good, and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says no, it is
comparable to the animal case and you can go ahead and be
מקריב makriv the קומץ kometz even though all the שיריים shirayim is
not there. And as we'll see later on, there's a question whether
you can eat the שיריים shirayim or not, but minimally according to
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan you can be מקריב makriv the קומץ. kometz.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, יתיב רב פפא וקאמר להאי
שמעתא, yativ Rav Pappa veka’amar lehai shmaita, Rav Pappa was sitting and
telling over this debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש.
Reish Lakish. אמר ליה רב יוסף בר שמעיה, amar lei Rav Yosef
bar Shemaya, so
Rav Yosef bar Shemaya said to Rav Pappa, מי לא עסקינן דרבי
יוחנן וריש לקיש במנחת העומר דציבור הוא ופליגי? mi lo askinan deRabbi
Yochanan veReish Lakish beminchat ha'omer detzibur hu ufeligi? So the גמרא Gemara
had asked a question at the end of yesterday from a case
that by the לחם הפנים, Lechem HaPanim, that it was evident that
if some of it was missing you could still go ahead and
offer up the בזיכין, bazichin, which is effectively like the קומץ, kometz,
you could offer up the לבונה levona of the לחם הפנים Lechem
HaPanim if some of it went missing, and that was a proof
to רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. And ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, the גמרא
Gemara said, well, why couldn't ריש לקיש Reish Lakish say that's different
because it's a קרבן ציבור? korban tzibur? And the גמרא Gemara said
no, it wouldn't have made a difference if it was a קרבן
ציבור korban tzibur because קרבן ציבור korban tzibur doesn't get special status
for things like missing, it only gets special status for things like
טומאה. tuma. That was the end of the discussion yesterday. And here
we're
saying maybe the reason the גמרא Gemara also couldn't have given the
קרבן ציבור korban tzibur is different answer, why ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
couldn't have offered that to explain the challenge from the case of
the לחם הפנים, Lechem HaPanim, is because maybe their whole debate was
also about a קרבן ציבור, korban tzibur, about a
מנחת עומר, minchat omer, who says that they were just talking about
a קרבן יחיד? korban yachid? Okay,
דציבור הוא ופליגי. detzibur hu ufeligi. אמר רב מלכיו, amar Rav Malkio,
okay, so the גמרא Gemara doesn't really have an answer to that,
but it's another reason why the גמרא Gemara could not have made
that distinction. So in the end, from the לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim
is a good proof to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that even if
some of it was missing you can go ahead and be מקריב
makriv the קומץ. kometz. Okay, אמר רב מלכיו, amar Rav Malkio, so
Rav Malkio said, תנא חדא מסלתה, tana chada misolta, new point here,
I mean, still the same discussion but new point.
תנא חדא, tana chada, one ברייתא braita teaches, מסלתה, misolta, you shall
offer up the קומץ הכהן מסלתה, hakometz hakohen misolta, you should take
the קמיצה kmitza from the
סלת, solet, that's telling you all of the סלת, solet, all of
the flour, שאם חסרה כל שהוא פסולה, she'im chasera kol shehu psula,
that if some of it is missing it's invalid.
משמנה, mishemena, from its oil, שאם חסרה כל שהוא פסול, she'im chasera
kol shehu pasul, and if some of the oil is missing it's
invalid.
ותניא אידך, vetanya idach, so that learns out the problem of a
מנחה mincha being חסר chaser from those words. ותניא אידך, vetanya idach,
and another ברייתא braita teaches, והנותרת מן המנחה, vehanoseres min hamincha, what
is left over from the מנחה mincha shall be for אהרן Aaron
and his kids, פרט למנחה שחסרה היא, perat lemincha shechasera hi, so
what's left over from the entire מנחה, mincha, which is coming to
exclude a case that some of the מנחה mincha went
missing, שחסרה וחסר קומצה, shechasera vechaser komtza, or maybe you don't have
the full
קומץ, kometz, ושלא הצית מלבונתה כלום, veshelo hitzit milevontah klum, or you
did not offer up any part of the לבונה, levona, because while
the case by the קומץ kometz is that even if a little
is missing from the קומץ kometz it's invalid, by the לבונה levona
it's the opposite is true, as long as you offer up a
tiny bit of the לבונה levona even if not the full amount
it's כשר, kosher, we'll see about that later. Anyway, he says you
have two ברייתות braitot which are learning out from different פסוקים psukim
this problem of חסר. chaser. Why do you need two ברייתות braitot
to teach you that? So he says like this, he says, תרי
קראי בחסרה למה לי? trei kray bechasera lama li? Why do you
need two פסוקים psukim to tell you the problem of חסר? chaser?
לאו, lav, wouldn't it be that they're coming to tell you two
different scenarios of חסר? chaser? What would that be? לאו חד למנחה
שחסרה קודם קמיצה, lav chad lemincha shechasera kodem kmitza, one to tell
you that if some of the מנחה mincha went missing before the
קמיצה, kmitza, because it says וקמץ משם מסלתה וקמץ משם מסלתה ומשמנה,
vekomatz misham misolta vekomatz misham misolta umishemena, it's talking about the act
of קמיצה, kmitza, so if some of it was lacking before the
קמיצה kmitza it's
invalid, because that was one
פסוק. passuk. וחד לשיריים שחסרו בין קמיצה להקטרה, vechad leshirayim shechasru bein
kmitza lehaktara, and the other that says והנותרת מן המנחה, vehanoseres min
hamincha, which is talking about what's left over, the שיריים, shirayim, is
to tell you that if some went missing between the קמיצה kmitza
and the הקטרה, haktara, the offering up, that it's invalid, that it's
also invalid if some went missing
after the קמיצה kmitza but before it was offered up. And if
that's what... those two are talking about and that is the context
of both of those פסוקים, psukim, then it would lead
to תיובתא לרבי יוחנן בתרווייהו. tiyuvta l'Rabbi Yochanan bitravaihu. The case that
both of these scenarios are a contradiction to רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan.
Why? Because yesterday we said that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish debated what's the story if some of it went
missing before קמיצה kmitza where רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said you could
refill it and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said you could not. Okay,
and here it seems like one פסוק pasuk is telling you that
if it was חסר chaser at the time of קמיצה kmitza it's
invalid. That seems to prove like ריש לקיש Reish Lakish that you
can't refill. Okay, and then the other one is the debate we've
been talking about if it went missing between קמיצה kmitza and הקטרה
haktara where רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says it's still valid and presumably
this extra פסוק pasuk is telling you that it's invalid. So doesn't
this both of these side with ריש לקיש Reish Lakish that both
of these scenarios it's invalid? That's a pretty good question. Let's see
what the גמרא Gemara says. לא חד למנחה שחסרה קודם קמיצה. Lo
chad l'mincha shechasra kodem kmitza. You are right that the first one
is that the מנחה mincha is lacking before קמיצה kmitza it's invalid,
but it's not a proof to ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. Why? Because
what it's telling you is the
following: דמייתי מביתו דאם איתנו אין ולא לא. d'maiti m'beito d'im iteinu
in v'lo lo. It's telling you that if it went lacking and
you took the קמיצה kmitza while it was still lacking, it is
invalid. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan never said you could take the קמיצה
kmitza from a מנחה mincha that was lacking. He just said that
if it went lacking before קמיצה kmitza you could refill it, you
could fill up the part that was missing
from extra flour and oil from your house. Okay, so yes, you
are right. It tells you that if it's lacking at the time
of קמיצה kmitza it's invalid. That is completely not relevant to the
debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. They
both agree to that. They're only debating whether is it allowed to
refill it if you refilled it before you took the קמיצה. kmitza.
But if you didn't refill it, they both agree it's invalid. So
that's that point. How about the other point about lacking? If it
says lacking is a problem in a case of שיירים, shirayim, isn't
that a proof like ריש לקיש? Reish Lakish? So let's see what
it says.
חד לשיריים שחסרו בין קמיצה לקטורת. chad l'shirayim shechasru bein kmitza l'ketores.
You are right, it is the scenario of שיירים shirayim that some
of the שיירים shirayim went missing between קמיצה kmitza and קטורת. ketores.
So why wouldn't it be a proof to ריש לקיש? Reish Lakish?
No, because what it's telling you is דאף על גב דמקטיר קומץ
עליהן עושין שיירים אסורין לאכילה. d'af al gav d'maktir kometz aleihen osin
shirayim asurin l'achila. That even though you can bring the קומץ, kometz,
the שיירים shirayim would be forbidden. So the second פסוק pasuk that
is telling you והנותרת מן המנחה, vehanoteret min hamincha, the end of
that פסוק pasuk is יאכלו אהרן ובניו. yochlu Aharon uvanav. So that
is telling you if the שיירים shirayim go lacking you have a
problem, but the problem isn't that you can't offer the קטורת. ketores.
You can offer the קטורת ketores according to רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan.
It's telling you והנותרת מן המנחה vehanoteret min hamincha you have to
have all the שיירים shirayim there when the קומץ kometz is offered
in order יאכלו אהרן ובניו yochlu Aharon uvanav to be able to
eat the שיירים. shirayim. Okay, and דאיבעיא להו, d'ibaia lehu, we raised
the question, לדברי אומר שיירים שחסרו בין קמיצה לקטורת מקטיר קומץ עליהן.
l'divrei omer shirayim shechasru bein kmitza l'ketores maktir kometz aleihen. According to
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that says when they went
missing between the קמיצה kmitza and the קטורת ketores you can still
go ahead and offer up and do the
קטורת, ketores, אותן שיירים מה הן באכילה? otan shirayim ma hen b'achila?
What is the story? Fine, you could offer up the קומץ kometz
because the קומץ kometz was done validly when it was complete. Now
offer up the קומץ. kometz. But at the time the קומץ kometz
was offered, which is מתיר matir the שיירים, shirayim, so the שיירים
shirayim aren't in a good state. So can the שיירים shirayim be
eaten in that case? So that's the question. זירי אמר, Zeiri amar,
so אמר זירי אמר קרא והנותרת ולא
הנותרת מן הנותרת. amar Zeiri amar kra vehanoteret v'lo hanoteret min hanoteret.
So זירי Zeiri says no, they cannot be eaten because it says
what remains shall be eaten by אהרן ובניו, Aharon uvanav, and not
what remains from what remains. So if you took the קמיצה kmitza
in a normal case and the שיירים shirayim are complete, the שיירים
shirayim are what remains. But if something went missing from those שיירים,
shirayim, then what's left is the remains of the remains, and that
cannot be eaten. So that's similar to the דרשה drasha of the
ברייתא, braita, והנותרת מן המנחה vehanoteret min hamincha only if it is
left over from the full מנחה mincha can it be eaten and
otherwise it cannot be eaten. And רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would agree
with that. It can't be eaten, but you can still offer up
the קומץ. kometz. Okay, so that's
זירי. Zeiri. רב ינאי אמר מהמנחה ממנחה שהייתה כבר. Rav Yannai amar
mehamincha mimincha shehayta kvar. From the מנחה mincha that already was. Now
what is that saying? So רש"י Rashi has two different interpretations. One
is that he's arguing with זירי Zeiri and he's actually saying as
long as it was a good מנחה mincha when you took the
קומץ, kometz, then you can go ahead and eat the שיירים shirayim
even though it was not a full מנחה mincha when the קומץ
kometz was offered up. Okay, and that would be then they would
be debating that question and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would be coming
down on the side of זירי Zeiri that you cannot offer it
up, there is a problem with חסר chaser in terms of eating
the שיירים. shirayim. The other language... דרשה drasha from the פסוק. pasuk.
Okay, and that would be, you know, then they would be debating
that question, and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would come be coming down
on the side of זעירי Zeiri that you cannot offer it up,
there is a problem with חסר chasar in terms of eating the
שירים. shirayim. The other לשון Lashon רש"י Rashi has is that רבי
ינאי Rabbi Yanai is also saying no, it had to be a
full מנחה Mincha when you offered it up, and he's really agreeing
to זעירי, Zeiri, he's just emphasizing a different דרשה drasha from the
פסוק. pasuk. Okay, so that's the end of the debate of רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, what do you do with
the... if it went missing between קמיצה kmitza and שירים? shirayim? ריש
לקיש Resh Lakish says you can't offer the קמיצה, kmitza, רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan says you can offer the קמיצה, kmitza, but the גמרא
Gemara seems to be coming down on the side that you cannot
eat the שירים. shirayim. Okay, now back to the משנה. Mishnah. Okay,
that was the end of that long description. קמץ בשמאלו, Komatz bismolo,
the משנה Mishnah says that if a קמיצה kmitza is done with
the left hand, it is invalid. And this is now what we're
going to focus on on the rest of today's דף, daf, the
issue of using a left hand for קמיצה kmitza and for other
things. מנא הני מילי? Menani milei? Where's this from? That you can't
do קמיצה kmitza with the left hand? אמר רבי זירא אמר קרא,
Amar Rabbi Zeira amar krah, says רבי זירא, Rabbi Zeira, the פסוק
pasuk says, והקריב את המנחה ומלא כפו ממנה, vehikriv et hamincha vemilei
kapa mimena, he brought forward the מנחה Mincha and אהרן Aaron filled
his hand with it, his palm with it. כף אני לא יודע
מהו, Kaf ani lo yodeiah mahu, I don't know the story about
this palm, is it your right palm or your left palm? כשהוא
אומר ולקח הכהן לוג השמן, Keshehu omer velakach hakohen log hashamen, when
it talks about the קרבן korban of the מצורע, metzora, and it
says the כהן kohen shall take from the לוג log of oil,
ויצק על כף הכהן השמאלית, veyatzak al kaf hakohen hasmalit, and he
pours with his right hand and he pours it into the palm
of his left hand. So what does that teach you? That teaches
you the following. כאן שמאלית כל מקום שנאמר כף אינו אלא ימין.
Kan smalit, hokol makom shene'emar kaf einu ela yamin. Because here it
had to use the modifier left hand, so hand without a modifier
means the right hand. The גמרא Gemara does this at various times,
like it does this by עדים, eidem, it's a classic case.
In one place it says כי יקום עד אחד באיש, ki yakum
eid echad be'ish, when a single witness rises up against a person,
so the גמרא Gemara says because it had to modify it and
say a single witness, it means just saying עד eid by itself
means two witnesses. Okay, so here because it had to say your
left palm, it means palm by itself means your right palm, and
since it says your palm by the קמיצה kmitza of a מנחה,
Mincha, we learn that that has to be with the right and
not the left. Okay, that seems like a pretty straightforward דרשה, drasha,
let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. דהאי
מיבעי ליה לגופיה? Dehai miba'ei lei legufeih? One minute, don't you need
שמאלית smalit not to infer what unmodified כף kaf means, but just
to say here left is
required? All right, so דהאי מיבעי ליה לגופיה? dehai miba'ei lei legufeih?
שמאלית אחרינא כתיב. Smalit achrina ktiv. No, it says שמאלית smalit twice,
because it says in the פרשה, parsha, it says, you know, twice
when it's describing, it says pour on the כף השמאלית kaf hasmalit
and take the oil from the כף השמאלית. kaf hasmalit. It says
שמאלית smalit twice. So the second one is certainly superfluous, it's already
clear that it was poured onto the left palm. Okay, so the
second one is coming to tell you that only here שמאלית smalit
is it שמאלית, smalit, but normally כף kaf means the right.
So the גמרא Gemara says ואימא
אין מיעוט אחר מיעוט אלא לרבות? ve'eima ein mi'ut achar mi'ut ela
lerabbot? Well, one minute, if it says שמאלית smalit twice, rather than
using that to tell you only here and not elsewhere, maybe it's
saying the opposite, that it doesn't have to be left, it could
even be right. This is a very ironic point, you know, דרשה
drasha that the גמרא Gemara has. If it says something twice, maybe
it's coming to say, like, methinks thou dost protest too much, that
you know, by saying, demanding it twice, it's actually saying it doesn't
have to be specifically that. Don't ask me about that principle. But
anyway, so maybe by saying it twice it means it could even
be a right hand, you know.
ואימא אין מיעוט אחר מיעוט אלא לרבות. ve'eima ein mi'ut achar mi'ut
ela lerabbot. So גמרא Gemara says שמאלית אחרינא
כתיב. Smalit achrina ktiv. It says שמאלית smalit yet a third time
because it talks about a מצורע metzora who doesn't have enough money
for bringing all the animal sacrifices and he can bring some of
the sacrifices as birds, and it describes the whole process again, and
in this second case it actually says שמאלית smalit by the palm
two more times. So we're going to get up to number four
in a minute. So the גמרא Gemara says no, it says it
a third time, so the third time tells me don't say that
it's coming twice to say even right hand, no it means specifically
left, and only
here left and not elsewhere. So the גמרא Gemara says ואימא אדרבא
מה כאן שמאלית אף בעלמא נמי שמאלית? ve'eima adaraba ma kan smalit
af be'alma nami smalit? Well okay, three times tells me that we
really really mean left, we're not saying it twice to mean right,
we're saying it three times to really really mean left, but maybe
this is a paradigm, maybe this is to teach you that anywhere
that it says כף kaf it means the left rather than your
point that only here. Maybe this is telling you this is the
model. So the גמרא Gemara says ארבע שמאלית כתיב, arba smalit ktiv,
it says שמאלית... smalit... It says four times תרי בעני ותרי בעשיר
*trei be'ani ve'trei be'ashir*. As I said, two in the case of
the קרבן Korban *korban* of a poor מצורע Metzora? *metzora*, two by
the case of the one can afford the full קרבן Korban *korban*,
and somehow רש"י Rashi *Rashi* tries to do the math, I'm not
going to try to figure it out, but somehow because it says
it four times that tells me it really means left hand here,
it doesn't mean right hand, and it's only required here and here
only is it left hand, and it is not a model for
elsewhere, but the general rule is that כף kaf. *kaf* by itself
means right. Okay, fine.
That's one דרשה Drasha *drasha*, that because כף kaf *kaf* is the
keyword and at one place it had to be modified with left,
then it means the default is right. אמר ליה רבי ירמיה לרבי
זירא *amalei Rabi Yirmiya le-Rabi Zeira*, רבי ירמיה *Rabi Yirmiya* said to
רבי זירא *Rabi Zeira*, על בהן ידו הימנית ועל בהן רגלו הימנית
דכתיב למה לי *al bohen yado hayemanis ve'al bohen raglo hayemanis d'ksiv
lama li*. So if you're going to make a דרשה Drasha *drasha*
from the fact that it says שמאלית *smalis* here is to teach
you that generally כף kaf *kaf* means your right, what do you
do with the fact that the תורה Torah *Torah* is constantly in
fact also using the modifier of right? Because what the תורה *Torah*
says is when you put the blood of the קרבן Korban *korban*
of the מצורע Metzora? *metzora*, you put it on his earlobe and
on his right thumb, his right earlobe, his right thumb, and his
right toe. That's about the blood and it says the word right,
right, right all those times there, ימנית ימנית ימנית *yemanis yemanis yemanis*.
And then it says you put the oil of the that you
just poured on your left hand, the כהן Kohen *kohen*, on top,
where the blood is, so it already says where the blood is,
and then it goes and repeats the right lobe, the right thumb,
the right toe. So that's a lot of repetition there,
especially once it already said you put it where the blood is.
So what do you need all of that for, all of the
right by when it's talking about where you put the oil? If
you're going to make a דרשה drasha *drasha* about left, why don't
you make, what's the דרשה drasha *drasha* you're going to make about
right? So למה לי *lama li*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* now
says top of י עמוד amud. א *yud amud aleph*.
And if you see the parentheses, I take it out here, they
were probably later glosses to clarify, but it's והא כתיב דם האשם
*ve'ha'ksiv dam ha'asham*, it already says you put it where the blood
is, why is it saying right, right, right where it's talking about
the oil? חד להכשיר צדדין וחד לפסול צידי צדדין *chad lehachshir tzdadin
ve'chad lifsol tzidei tzdadin*. Okay, so there it's insisting, and later we're
going to say the emphasis here is not on the fact that
it says right, but why does it even have to say thumb
and ear and
toe? It already said you put it where you put the blood
of the אשם asham. *asham*, why is it repeating all the body
parts? And to tell you that it's telling you, on the one
hand it's telling you that it has to, it doesn't have to
be like on exactly on the surface of the thumb, it can
even be at the edges of the thumb. Okay, so it says
the word thumb again to tell you we're being a little bit
more expansive, it can even be on the edges of the thumb,
of the sun, of the thumb. Okay, and the other is to
tell
you that it can't be on the edges of the edges, which
רש"י *Rashi* says means the underside of the thumb.
So the two times that it says it is again, once it
says it by the קרבן korban. *korban* of the rich מצורע Metzora
*metzora* which is bringing actually the mammals, and the other by the
poor one which is bringing the birds. So and as I said,
we're not yet up to the issue of right. Why does the
תורה *Torah* have to say by both of those קרבנות Korbanot, *korbanos*
thumb, toe, and ear again if it already said where you put
the blood of the אשם asham. *asham* is? So it's telling you
that it can be an expansive definition of thumb, even the sides,
but it can't be the underside. And that's the second one is
to tell you it can't be the underside.
Okay, now we're going to דרשן *darshan* why it's the פסוקים *psukim*
about where the blood is, and then we're going to go back
to the emphasis of the multiple explanations why it has to say
right and so on. But now we're still focusing on it says
put it where the blood is on the thumb. So we first
said why does it have to say thumb, it said where the
blood was, to tell you even the sides of the thumb. And
now we're going to look at the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* of where
the blood is. על דם האשם *al dam ha'asham*, where the blood
of the אשם asham. *asham* is, על מקום דם האשם *al mekom
dam ha'asham*, and another פסוק *pasuk* says the place where the blood
of the אשם asham? *asham* is. So what are we supposed to
infer from those different articulations? למאי אתו הני *lemai asu hani*? What
do you need, למאי אתו הני *lemai asu hani*? צריכי *tzerichi*, you
need both. אי כתב רחמנא *ei kasav rachmana*, על דם האשם *al
dam ha'asham*, where the blood is, הוה אמינא איתיה אין נתקנח לא
*hava amina isai in niskanach lo*. The blood has to still be
there, and if it was wiped off of his thumb or his
ear, it's invalid because the oil has to be put on the
blood. So כתב רחמנא על מקום *kasav rachmana al mekom*, it says
the place where the blood is, as long as it's the same
place, even if it was wiped away. ואי כתב רחמנא על מקום
*ve'ei kasav rachmana al mekom*, if it just said put it in
the place where the blood is, הוה אמינא דוקא נתקנח *hava amina
davka niskanach*, I would have said you have to wipe it away.
It's the place, but the blood can't be there. Why? אבל איתיה
*Aval isei* cause if the blood was there, אימא הוה חציצה *eima
hava chatzitzah* maybe that would be a חציצה *chatzitzah* between the oil
and the thumb. קמשמע לן על דם האשם *Kamashma lan al dam
ha-asham*. Okay, so that's just a nice דיוק *diyuk*. It says where
the on the blood and the place of the blood to tell
you that either is okay, directly on the blood or there's no
blood and where the blood was. Okay. אמר רבא Rava *Amar Rava*.
Now we're going to get back to the the right, that it
says right, right, right multiple times. Okay, מאחר דכתיב על דם האשם
ועל מקום דם האשם *me-achar de-chasiv al dam ha-asham ve-al makom dam
ha-asham*, so it says you put it where, you know, the place
of the blood, דכתיבא ימינית בדם *de-chasiva yeminis be-dam* and when it
speaks about the blood it says right lobe, right thumb, right toe,
okay, על בוהן ידו הימנית ועל בוהן רגלו הימנית *al bohen yado
ha-yemanis ve-al bohen raglo ha-yemanis*, okay, so it says right, על בוהן
ידו הימנית ועל בוהן רגלו הימנית *al bohen yado ha-yemanis ve-al bohen
raglo ha-yemanis*, ודכתיב בשמן דמצורע עשיר Ashir, ועני למה לי *u-de-chasiv be-shemen
de-metzora ashir ve-ani lama li*? So why do I have to say
right, right, right all those times? You told me it repeats thumb
and toe to tell you even the edges. But why does it
repeat the fact that it's the right thumb and the right toe
if you already told me where the blood is? If we're going
to make a דרשה drasha *drasha* about why it says left to
teach me that normally hand means right, what are you going to
do with why it says right all of these times? So אלא
אמר רבא Rava *ela amar Rava*, so Rava says here's how here's
what I'm learning out. Not
what you learned about about כף *kaf* means right, I'm going to
make the דרשה drasha *drasha* of קמיצה Kmitza *kemitzah* from the not
an inference from where it says left by the palm that the
כף *kaf* by קמיצה Kmitza *kemitzah* means right, I'm going to make
the learn out the idea of the right hand by קמיצה Kmitza,
*kemitzah* from all the repetitions of right which it says by the
מצורע Metzora. *metzora*. Okay, and I'll learn out other places that you
need the right of the body part as opposed to the left
because of the repetitions of the word right by the מצורע Metzora
*metzora*. אלא אמר רבא Rava יד יד yad yad לקמיצה רגל רגל
לחליצה אוזן אוזן לרציעה *ela amar Rava yad yad le-kemitzah regel regel
le-chalitzah ozen ozen le-retziah*. Okay, and it repeats it says ידו הימנית
*yado ha-yemanis*
which where it was redundant by the מצורע Metzora *metzora* to tell
you elsewhere where you need a hand, it also has to be
your right hand. Where is that elsewhere? הקמיצה *ha-kemitzah* of the מנחה
mincha, *mincha*. Now it's a little bit of a problem because there
it speaks about כף *kaf* and not יד *yad*,
there's some discussion about maybe we can find a פסוק *pasuk* that
says יד *yad*, maybe it's enough that conceptually it refers to the
hand. But the יד ימינית *yad yemanis* that it says, the extra
ימינית *yemanis* that it says by מצורע Metzora *metzora* is to teach
you קמיצה's Kmitza *kemitzah's* with your right hand. רגל רגל לחליצה *Regel
regel le-chalitzah*, the fact that it speaks about your right toe is
to tell you, you know, that בוהן רגלו הימנית *bohen raglo ha-yemanis*,
the toe of your right foot is to tell you that when
the Torah says do a חליצה Chalitza, *chalitzah* with your רגל *regel*,
it means your right foot. Okay, so to teach you another place
the רגל *regel* has to be your right one. רגל רגל לחליצה
*Regel regel le-chalitzah*. And אוזן אוזן
לרציעה
*ozen ozen le-retziah*. When it speaks about the slave and putting a
hole in the ear and it doesn't say which ear, because here
it says the lobe of your right ear, from that we learn
that elsewhere the ear has to be the right ear as well.
So that's a very nice way, efficient way of using all the
extra words and to tell me all of these, you know, הלכות
Halachot *halachos* that I wouldn't have known whether it means the right
body part or the left body part or that it didn't matter.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says דעשיר למה אתא *de-ashir
lama asa* or דעני למה אתא *de-ani lama asa*. So that's great,
that's a great דרשה drasha. *drasha*. But remember, it says everything twice.
It says it by the קרבן korban *korban* of the rich מצורע
metzora *metzora* and of the poor מצורע metzora *metzora*. So you now
explained why you needed the ימינית *yemanis* by at least by one
of them. What do we do with all the use of the
word ימינית *yemanis* by the other קרבן *korban* of the מצורע metzora,
*metzora*, by the קרבן *korban* of the מצורע metzora, *metzora* who's poor?
Why did it have to repeat ימינית *yemanis* there? אמר רב ששת
בריה דרב אידי *Amar Rav Sheshes berei de-Rav Idi* לפסול ימין Yamin?
דכהן במצורע *lifsol yamin de-Kohen be-metzora*. To tell you that
oh wait, excuse me, excuse me, I misread that. I skipped the
key word there. Let's go back. Okay. אלא אמר רבא Rava יד
יד yad yad לקמיצה רגל רגל לחליצה אוזן אוזן לרציעה *Ela amar
Rava yad yad le-kemitzah regel regel le-chalitzah ozen ozen le-retziah*. Now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says שמאלית למה אתא *semalis lama asa*? Okay, so
excuse me. Now that we're we're not in we're going back to
why does it say left all those times, okay, by the, you
know, by the palm of the כהן Kohen *Kohen*? All right, before
we said it said left by the palm of the כהן Kohen
*Kohen* to tell me that the קמיצה kmitza? *kemitzah* has to be
with the right hand. But רבא Rava? *Rava* is saying we know
that קמיצה kmitza? *kemitzah* is a right hand because of the use
of the word right by right, right, right that it says by
the מצורע metzora? *metzora*. So if that's true, what's the insistence on
left, left, left when it's talking about the palm of the of
the כהן Kohen, *Kohen*? So שמאלית למה אתא *semalis lama asa*? So
אמר רב ששת בריה דרב אידי *amar Rav Sheshes berei de-Rav Idi*
לפסול ימין yamin. דכהן במצורע *lifsol yamin de-Kohen be-metzora*. To tell you
that when it says your the left palm, not to tell you
something about קמיצה. kmitza קמיצה kmitzah we know is right hand because
it says right, right, right. Okay, but the reason it says left,
left, left by the palm of the כהן Kohen, is to teach
you something about that case itself. That left is when it says
on his left palm, it's not saying even his left is okay.
Certainly you would assume right is good, normally we need right, but
even left is okay, but to tell you no, you only do
it with the left hand. Now part of that reason is because
you're pouring with your right hand, so you're only pouring
it—the hand you're pouring into has to be your left hand. Okay,
but the left it is saying there is to say only left
and not even left.
Fine. So
for רבא Rava we learn out the right hand for קמיצה kmitzah
by right, right, right, that it says by כהן kohein and that
also teaches you right body parts for other הלכות and the left,
left, left where it speaks about catching the oil is to say
only left and not right.
So now the גמרא Gemara says ואידך שמאל
ויד
ורגל ימין דעני למאי אתא. Ve’idach smol veyad veregel yamin de’ani lemai
ata. So okay, that explains why it says left, left, left in
one of the קרבנות, Korbanot, either the rich or the poor. But
how about why it says left, left, left in the other קרבן
of the מצורע? metzora Why was it said that many times? And
also why did it say right, right, right by the other קרבן
of the מצורע? So you have now explained one set of right,
right, right is to tell you the default is right body parts
for
קמיצה, kmitzah for the עבד, Eved, for חליצה, chalitza and left, left,
left is to tell you only the left. What do you need
by the other קרבן of the מצורע all of that right, right,
right and left, left, left? So the גמרא Gemara. says לכדתנא דבי
רבי ישמעאל. Lechidetana d’bei Rabbi Yishmael. Now that's not really teaching you
anything, like they teach in the house of רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael.
What did they say in the house of רבי ישמעאל? Rabbi Yishmael?
כל פרשה שנאמרה ונשנית לא נשנית אלא בשביל דבר שנתחדש בה, Kol
parsha shenemra venishnis lo nishnis ela bishvil davar shenischadesh bah, that if
something is being retold, sometimes it will
be a whole thing is being said to teach you one הלכה.
Halacha. So since one of the קרבנות, let's say the one of
the עשיר, it had to say right, right, right and left, left,
left to teach you these things, it's going to say it again
in the other one of the עני, Ani, even though it's not
really teaching you anything in the other time. Okay, that's a classic
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael approach
who says like דברה תורה כלשון בני אדם Dibra Torah kilshon bnei
adam
as opposed to a רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva approach who has to
learn out something new from every time it says something.
Okay, אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש.
Amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi
Shimon ben Lakish. Now that's how we learn out right by קמיצה
kmitzah and the elegant דרשה drasha is רבא because it says right
by the body parts by this case of the מצורע. Now we're
going to have another basis to say when do you need your
right hand? Okay, so let's take a look. אמר רבה בר בר
חנה אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש, Amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar
Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish, כל מקום שנאמר אצבע וכהונה אינה אלא ימין.
Kol makom shenemra etzba vekhuna eina ela yamin. Wherever it says finger
and כהונה, Kehuna, it has to be your right finger, and that
is because by the חטאת Chatat it says the כהן kohein shall
dip his finger and he shall place it on the corners of
the מזבח Mizbe’ach and there it explicitly says the right finger. So
that teaches you it’s a similar דרשה drasha to the one we
made before by the מצורע but that teaches you wherever the תורה
says finger and כהונה Kehuna or כהן, kohein we’ll see about that
in a minute, it requires the right. So now the גמרא Gemara
says like this, קא
סלקא דעתך, Ka salka d’atach, we are assuming אצבע וכהונה בעינן, Etzba
u’khuna be’inan, that it has to say both finger and כהונה Kehuna
to mean the right,
כדכתיב Kidechsiv and that would be like it says in the case
by the חטאת, Chatat, ולקח הכהן, Velakach haKohen, there's כהן, kohein. מדם
החטאת, Midam hachatat,
באצבעו, Be’etzbao, with his finger. Okay, so it says both of them
and that becomes the
basis to say that it always requires that. Okay, now how do
you know, by the way, that by that case it is ימין?
yamin. Okay, so רש"י says we learn that from the מצורע because
by the מצורע it says וטבל הכהן את אצבעו. Vetaval haKohen et
etzbao. וטבל הכהן את אצבעו הימנית. v'taval hakohein et etzba'o hayemanit. So
there also it says כהן kohein and אצבע etzba and ימין. So
we're going to assume that when it says both כהן kohein, and
אצבע etzba it means ימין. That's what the... this רבה בר בר
חנה Rabbah bar bar Chana is teaching us.
Okay so now the גמרא's Gemara going to challenge this. וגמר... vegamar...
I'm sorry, it's not רש״י, Rashi, it's the גמרא. Gemara I'm reading
רש״י. Rashi. וגמר מדם אצבע אצבע וגמר ממצורע דכתיב
וטבל הכהן את אצבעו הימנית. v'gamar middam etzba etzba vegamar mimmetzora dechtiv
v'taval hakohein et etzba'o hayemanit. Okay so it says כהן kohein. and
אצבע etzba and right hand and right by the מצורע and it
says it by חטאת chatas and that's going to be the basis
that every time it says both of those you're going to need
right. All right.
So now the גמרא Gemara challenges this. והרי קמיצה דלא כתיבא בה
אלא כהונה. v'harei kmitza delo chetiva bah ella kehuna.
What about קמיצה? kmitzah, It doesn't say right. It just says כהן.
kohein It doesn't say אצבע. etzba. It says כף. Maybe כף we've
learned before to apply the idea of יד ימין yad yamin to
כף but it certainly doesn't say אצבע. etzba. So and presumably this
is coming to replace the need for other דרשות drashot about the
right. Okay. והרי קמיצה דלא כתיבא בה אלא כהונה ותנן קמץ בשמאל
פסול.
v'harei kmitza delo chetiva bah ella
kehuna utnan kamatz bismol pasul. That you have to, you can't do
קמיצה בשמאל. kmitza bismol. So we've had other דרשות drashot from מצורע
but this is seeming to say that we're learning it from the
use of כהן kohein and אצבע. etzba. So how does that apply...
how do you learn out this principle by
קמיצה? kmitzah. So
אמר רבא או אצבע או כהונה. amar Rava o etzba o kehuna.
No, no, no. What we learn is either one. Either if it
says finger or it says כהן, kohein it's going to require the
right. Okay now it almost always says כהן. kohein So based on
this דרשה drasha it's basically going to say anything a כהן kohein
has to do he has to do with his right body part.
אמר ליה אביי. amar lei Abbaye. So אביי Abbaye said, והרי הולכת
איברים לכבש דכתיב בהו כהונה. v'harei holachat evarim lakevesh dechtiv behu kehuna.
One minute, there are things that says כהן kohein that doesn't require
the right body part. Bringing the limbs of the עולה olah to
the ramp. Okay it says כהונה. kehuna. דכתיב והקריב הכהן את הכל
המזבחה, dechtiv vehikriv hakohein et hakkol hammizbeachah, he should bring it all
to the altar. ואמר מר, ve'amar mar, we teach זו הולכת איברים
לכבש, zu holachat evarim lakevesh, this is bringing the limbs to the
ramp. ותנן, utnan, and how do I know that wasn't limited to
the right hand? Because the משנה mishna teaches, הראש והרגל הראש בימינו
והרגל של ימין בשמאלו, harosh veharegel harosh biymino veharegel shel yamin bismolo,
it describes how they would bring the different body parts of the
עולה. olah. It says he would take the head in his right
hand and he would take the leg, the right leg, and in
his left hand, ובית ערוה לחוץ, uveit ervah lachutz, and you know,
the place of the genitals would be facing outside. Anyway so you
see you bring the... you do this thing where it says כהן
kohein and you do it with your left hand. Okay, so it
can't be every time it says כהן kohein. it has to be
right. So the גמרא Gemara says no, כי אמרן או אצבע או
כהונה בדבר המעכב כפרה. ki amran o etzba o kehuna bedavar hamme'akkeiv
kapparah. No, no, no, that would only be something like the sprinkling
of the blood of the חטאת chatas or the putting of the
blood or whatever on the מצורע, where it is a necessary part
of what makes it a legitimate קרבן. Okay, bringing the limbs to
the ramp is not something that is necessary. Even, even for offering
them, if you שחט shachted it right by the altar, there's not
a requirement to do this conveyance of them to the ramp. Okay,
so it's not a necessary עבודה. avoda. But where it says כהן
kohen. or finger and it's something that is a necessary עבודה, avoda,
that would have to be right. And that's how we learn out
קמיצה kemitza, and that's how we would learn out many, many things.
All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says
is this really true? Let's take a look.
והרי קבלה. v'harei kabbala. How about catching the blood? דדבר המעכב כפרה
הוא. didvar hamme'akkeiv kapparah hu. That obviously is הלכה halachically required, it's
מעכב כפרה, me'akkeiv kapparah, וכתיב בה כהונה, vechtiv bah kehuna, and it
mentions, it says כהונה. kehuna. דכתיב והקריבו בני אהרן הכהנים את הדם,
dechtiv vehikrivu bnei Aharon hakohanim et hadam, they shall bring close the
blood. וזו, vezu, and we say what does that mean? וזו קבלת
הדם, vezu kabbalat hadam, that is catching the blood. Now you're probably
thinking to yourself yeah, קבלת הדם kabbalat hadam does require the right,
every of the classic עבודות avodot requires the right. ותנן, utnan, so
we taught in the משנה mishna in זבחים, Zevachim, קיבל בשמאל פסול.
kibel bismol pasul. Getting if you did the קבלה kabbala with your
left, it's invalid. Great, that's what I would have expected. So far
everything works. אה ורבי שמעון מכשיר, ah v'Rabbi Shimon machshir, but רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it's okay. Now I don't know what a
big challenge that is, you know, you have a bizarre position of
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. We're trying to explain the default position that
you require right and that we're going to do from כהן kohen
or אצבע. etzba. But fine, we want to understand רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon. How does רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon fit in to this idea?
So the גמרא Gemara says ורבי שמעון קאמרת? u'v'Rabbi Shimon ka'amart? You're
challenging me with רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? רבי
שמעון תרתי בעי.
Rabbi Shimon
tarti ba'ei. רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, it's true, he needs both כהן
kohen. and אצבע. etzba. The reason רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says קבלה
kabbala works is because it only says כהן. Kohen? with left is
it only says כהן Kohen *Kohen* and it doesn't say אצבע etzba
*Etzba*. So the default position of the חכמים Chachamim *Chachamim* that pretty
much everything or everything that's essential requires right is based on learning
it from חטאת chatas *Chatat* and learning from מצורע *Metzora* where it
says כהן Kohen *Kohen* and אצבע *Etzba* and right, it certainly says
right by מצורע *Metzora* that anytime it says כהן Kohen, *Kohen* which
pretty much means every single place or anytime it says אצבע *Etzba*
as long as those are essential עבודות *avodot* needs right. And that's
the default. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* makes exceptions because he
says oh no, only if it says both כהן *Kohen* and אצבע
*Etzba*. And that's why the blood if you did it בשמאל *bismole*
is כשר *kosher*. So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says ומי בעי רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon תרתי *u'mi bay Rabbi Shimon tarti*? Is that really
true that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* would say you need
both כהן *Kohen* and אצבע *Etzba* and otherwise שמאל *smol* is okay?
והתניא *ve-hatanya* we taught in the ברייתא braisa *Braita*, רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon, אומר כל מקום שנאמר יד אינו אלא ימין *Rabbi Shimon omer
kol makom she'ne-emar yad eino ela yamin*, אצבע אינו אלא ימין *etzba
eino ela yamin*. Whenever it says יד *yad* it means right, אצבע
*etzba* it means right, which sort of sounds like our earlier דרשות
drashas, *drashot*. So he doesn't require that it both say כהן *Kohen*
and אצבע *Etzba*. Either one is enough. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says no, אצבע לא בעי כהונה kehuna, *etzba lo bay kehuna*. If
it says finger, it doesn't have to say כהן *Kohen*. Finger always
means the right finger. Fine.
And however כהונה בעי אצבע *kehuna bay etzba*. But when it says
כהן *Kohen*, anything that requires a כהן *Kohen* and says the word
כהן *Kohen*, that always has to be in the right. So to
repeat, for the חכמים *Chachamim*
anytime it says כהן *Kohen*, anytime it says אצבע *Etzba*, it has
to be wait I think I misstated that. For רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* when it says let me say it again אצבע
לא בעי כהונה *etzba lo bay kehuna* when it says אצבע *etzba*
that requires right even if it doesn't say כהן *Kohen*. כהונה בעי
אצבע *kehuna bay etzba* I think I misstated it before. If it
says כהן *Kohen* that does not require right. Only if it also
says כהן *Kohen* and אצבע *Etzba* which basically means that for רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* the word כהן *Kohen* is immaterial. רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon. *Rabbi Shimon* says as long as it says אצבע
*etzba* or יד *yad* I agree right hand. But כהן *Kohen* for
me that does not mean right hand. And the חכמים *Chachamim* say
even the word כהן *Kohen* by itself means right hand. And that's
how come they debate the case of קבלת הדם *kabbalat hadam*. קבלת
הדם *kabbalat hadam* says כהן *Kohen* but it doesn't say אצבע *etzba*.
So for the חכמים *Chachamim* כהן *Kohen* means right and for רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* no if you want right you need
it to say אצבע *etzba*. Okay so again to repeat for this
approach it's not it basically says anytime it says כהן *Kohen* which
is pretty much every single עבודה avoda *avoda* but as long as
if it's an essential עבודה *avoda* has to be right hand and
even if it says אצבע *etzba* by itself also right. רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* says I don't agree with your whole approach
to כהן *Kohen*. If you want it to mean right it has
to say אצבע *etzba*. If it just straight says כהן *Kohen* that
can be even left and that's why catching the blood can be
with the left. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says if
that's true אלא כהן למה לי *ela Kohen lama li*? So if
for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* כהן *Kohen* does not is
not being said to demand the use of the right why does
it say כהן *Kohen* by let's say קבלת הדם *kabbalat hadam*? So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says בכהונו *bi'kehuno* to tell you that he
has to be fully in his כהונה *kehuna* state which means he
has to be wearing בגדי כהונה *bigdei kehuna*. Fine. Top of י"א
עמוד ב *Yud Aleph amud beis*. So now we've got the lines
drawn between רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* and the חכמים *Chachamim*.
והרי זריקה zrikah *ve-harei zrika* how about the throwing of the blood?
דלא כתיב ביה אלא כהונה *delo ksiv bei ela kehuna* it doesn't
say אצבע *etzba*. Right anyway anything the תורה *Torah* describes as an
עבודה *avoda* that it doesn't need your finger it's not going to
say אצבע *etzba*. דלא כתיב ביה אלא כהונה *delo ksiv bei ela
kehuna* ודתנן *ve-detnan* we taught in the משנה Mishnah *Mishna* זרק בשמאל
פסול *zarak bismole pasul*. If you did זריקה zrikah *zrika* with the
left it's invalid ולא פליג רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *ve-lo palig Rabbi
Shimon* and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, *Rabbi Shimon* doesn't argue? Right how
could רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* say the only time you
need right is when it says אצבע *etzba*? How do you explain
the requirement of זריקה zrikah? *zrika* with your right? So the גמרא
Gemara, *Gemara* says אמר אביי פליגי בברייתא amar Abaye pligi bivraisa *amar
Abaye pligi be-braita* he does disagree with that okay in a ברייתא
*Braita* he says even the זריקה zerika. *zrika* doesn't have to be
the right hand. דתניא *detanya* we taught in a ברייתא *Braita* קיבל
בשמאל פסול ורבי שמעון מכשיר *kibel bismole pasul ve-Rabbi Shimon machshir* if
you caught with the left it's invalid and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
*Rabbi Shimon* says it's kosher we already saw that. And then the
real shocker זרק בשמאל פסול ורבי שמעון מכשיר *zarak בשמאל פסול ורבי
שמעון מכשיר* *zarak bismole pasul ve-Rabbi Shimon machshir*. If you did the
זריקה *zrika* the actual core עבודה *avoda* with the left it's invalid
with your left and רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* says it's okay. So
according to this רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* really according to the way
this emphasis on כהן *Kohen* and אצבע *etzba* etcetera the default is
anytime it says כהן *Kohen* especially if it's an essential עבודה *avoda*
requires right and that's why you always need the right hand and
comes along רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* and says nope only when it
says אצבע *etzba* you need right so קבלה kabbalah *kabbalah* and זריקה
*zrika* can be done with the left hand. Very interesting debate and
tying it into that question of the keyword of כהן *Kohen*. There's
a fascinating תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* here that says והרי זריקה ותנן זרק
בשמאל פסול *ve-harei zrika ve-tanan zarak bismole pasul*. So please רבי שמעון
אמר אביי פליגי בברייתא and תוספות Tosfos says תימה דאין זה משנה
בשום מקום. teimah de'ein zeh Mishnah beshum makom. Okay, the גמרא Gemara
says it's a משנה Mishnah that זריקה with the left is invalid
and תוספות Tosfos says this משנה Mishnah doesn't exist anymore. So that's
pretty funny. I mean, obviously on a certain level it's like, come
on, of course זריקה with your left has to be invalid. The
גמרא Gemara could have just sort of said, would רבי שמעון argue
even with זריקה? And it says, yes, in a ברייתא he argues.
But the גמרא Gemara says that it's a משנה Mishnah. and תוספות
Tosfos points out this is not a משנה. So תוספות Tosfos tries
to figure out maybe there's a different גירסא girsa in the גמרא,
Gemara whole long תוספות to figure that out.
Okay. ואלא, Ve'ella, now the גמרא Gemara says like this. ואלא הא
דאמר רבא יד יד לקמיצה למה לי מכוהנא נפקא? Ve'ella had amar
Rava yad yad le'kmitzah lama li mi'kehuna nafka? So now you're saying
that the basic learning of the right is from the word כהן.
So didn't רבא say you learn the idea of right from the
fact that it says ימין ימין ימין, yamin yamin yamin, right right
right, from in the case of a what do you call it,
in the case of the מצורע, and that one of those, two
of those were not related to כהונה, חליצה and the עבד, eved,
but the right by the hand was to tell you קמיצה kemitza
has to be with the right. So are we going to say
there's a debate? Does רבא work with this approach that learns out
the right from the word כהן then what's the דרשה drasha of
יד יד yad yad by the מצורע? So ואלא הא דאמר רבא
יד יד לקמיצה למה לי מכוהנא נפקא? Ve'ella had amar Rava yad
yad le'kmitzah lama li mi'kehuna nafka? So the גמרא Gemara says, yes,
we can make them both work.
חד לקומץ וחד לקידוש קומץ. Chad le'komitz ve'chad le'kidush kometz. קומץ. Kometz.
One is telling you the actual קמיצה kemitza, has to be with
your right hand, the taking of it,
of the oil and whatever from the מנחה, mincha. and the other
is putting that then into a כלי שרת, kli shares, that placing
into the כלי שרת kli shares also has to be with a
right hand. So that's why we learn it, we need both. Okay.
So the גמרא says לרבי שמעון le'Rabbi Shimon one minute, but לרבי
שמעון דלא בעי קידוש קומץ. le'Rabbi Shimon delo bei kidush kometz. So
one minute we later were about to
say where we learn later that for רבי שמעון you can actually
take the hand breath and and put it straight on the מזבח.
mizbe'ach. You don't have to put it in a כלי kli and
from the כלי kli put it on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So he
doesn't have that other step of putting it in a כלי. kli.
ולמאן דאמר נמי דבעי קידוש קומץ Ule'man de'amar nami debei kidush kometz
and even לרבי שמעון le'Rabbi Shimon בשמאל אכשורי מכשיר. bismol achshrei machshir.
So there are some that say that רבי שמעון would say yes
you do have to put it in a כלי, kli, but at
least would say that you can put it in a כלי kli
with your left hand. So one or the other version of רבי
שמעון, for רבי שמעון you cannot say that you need your right
for what do you call it, for two things. You might need
your right for doing the קמיצה kemitza itself,
but you don't need your right for putting it in the כלי,
kli, either because he doesn't require a
כלי kli all together or because he allows it with the left
hand. So according to that, יד יד דרבא למה לי? yad yad
de'Rava lama li? Why does he need the יד יד yad yad.
of רבא? Now it's a little funny because רבי שמעון we just
got through saying doesn't make the דרשה about כהן. So he might
just need the יד יד yad yad of רבא to tell you
the basic
קמיצה has to be with your right hand. No says the גמרא,
we know that from somewhere else according to רבי שמעון. אי לקמיצה
גופא אליבא דרבי שמעון מרבי יהודה בריה דרבי חייא נפקא. I'le'kmitzah gufah
aliba de'Rabbi Shimon mi'Rabbi Yehuda brei de'Rabbi Chiya nafka. That he learns
out from a teaching, so yet another לימוד limmud for the right
hand for קמיצה, a teaching of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda the son
of רבי חייא. Rabbi Chiya. דאמר רבי יהודה בריה דרבי חייא מאי
טעמא דרבי שמעון, De'amar Rabbi Yehuda brei de'Rabbi Chiya mai ta'ama de'Rabbi
Shimon, what's the reason of רבי שמעון that says that you don't
need to put it in a כלי kli is the point, not
the רבי שמעון we've been dealing with, but you don't need to
put it in a כלי kli after you do the
קמיצה. דאמר קרא, De'amar kra, the פסוק says, קודש קדשים היא. kodesh
kodashim hi. It's talking about the מנחה. mincha It is holy of
holies, כחטאת וכאשם. ke'chatas u'che'asham. So like a חטאת chatas. and an
אשם. asham. So what's the comparison to both of them? So רבי
שמעון says the
following. בא לעובדה ביד, Ba le'ovdah beyad,
if you want to use your hand and not put the קומץ
kometz into a כלי kli afterwards, עובדה בימין כחטאת, ovdah beyamin ke'chatas,
then use your left like a, use your right like a חטאת.
chatas In a certain way your hand is serving like the כלי
kli and therefore it has to be the right and the model
will be a חטאת chatas, where everything is with the right finger.
Okay. בא לעובדה בכלי, Ba le'ovdah bekli, if you're okay putting the
קומץ kometz into a
כלי, kli, if that's what you're going to do and then the
כלי kli serves as the כלי, kli, you don't need your hand
to serve as the כלי, kli, then in that case עובדה בשמאל
כאשם. ovdah bismol ke'asham. You can use your left like an אשם.
left like an אשם. What do you mean like an אשם? Well
like the case by the מצורע with pouring onto your left hand
and that's what the connection is to an אשם. So that's where
רבי שמעון learns that you don't have to put it into a
כלי. kli. You would have to use your right hand if you
weren't going to put it into a כלי, kli, but if you
put it, but you don't have to put it into a כלי.
kli. If you did put it into your כלי, kli, then you
could even use your you know your left hand to put it
into the כלי. kli. But what do you see from that? You
see that when you are using your hand for the original קמיצה,
it needs to be right. That's what we learn out from the
דרשה of כחטאת. k'chatas. The original קמיצה has to be right. If
you want to keep it just in your hand, keep it in
your right hand. If you want to transfer to a כלי, kli,
then you could do the transfer with your left. So now we
have the question
for not רבי שמעון
that you have to take it with your right hand and put
it into a כלי kli with your right hand. כהן? We have
two דרשות, כהן and יד יד. yad yad One tells us take
it with your right hand and the other says put it in
your כלי kli with your right hand. But for רבי שמעון, he
doesn't hold of the whole כהן דרשה. Fine. But what does he
need the יד יד yad yad. you know for the basic קמיצה,
he already knows your right hand because of the link to the
חטאת, chatas. כחטאת כאשם. k'chatas k'asham. So what does he need, and
he doesn't require putting it into a כלי kli with your right
hand, so what does he need the extra דרשה of יד יד
for? The גמרא says לא נצרכה אלא לקומץ דמנחת חוטא, Lo nitzrecha
ela l'kometz d'minchas choteh, and this gets back to like a point
the גמרא made on like the very first עמוד. You're right, the
basic stuff he doesn't need the extra דרשה of יד יד. But
for the מנחה mincha, of a חוטא, choteh,
of a you know, that's like the you know, that's a case
where you might have thought left hand would be okay. Why?
Because and this גמרא is a version of what the גמרא said
on דף ב. daf beis. The גמרא says like this.
סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka daitach amina, I would have thought הואיל ואמר
רבי שמעון שלא יהיה קרבנו מהודר Ho'il v'amar Rabbi Shimon shelo yehei
korbano mehudar that the reason there's no oil or לבונה levonah on
the מנחת חוטא, minchas choteh, you know for like somebody who brings
an עולה ויורד, oleh v'yored,
a variable חטאת.
Why is there no oil or לבונה? levonah? So it should not
be beautiful.
So therefore maybe we're trying to treat it as this type of
סוג ב sug bet type of a קרבן and you know treat
it in a haha left-handed manner, and therefore I would say כי
קמץ נמי בשמאל תכשר, Ki kamatz nami b'smol tichshar, maybe this left
hand would be good. קא משמע לן Ka mashma lan not even
this you need right hand. But what do we see from all
of this? We see that you require right. The basic דרשה of
the גמרא feels the broadest and most comfortable with is every time
it says כהן, certainly if it's an essential עבודה you need right.
רבי שמעון allows left in more places. It could be that he
specifically requires the דרשה of אצבע to demand right and therefore would
use left for קבלה and even for זריקה. And then there's similarly
by the case of the going back to the case of the
מנחה, mincha. you need a right hand according to the חכמים when
you take the קמיצה and when you put it into the כלי.
kli. But רבי שמעון actually has an interesting split. If you want
to, you don't have to put it in a כלי, kli, your
right hand can serve as the כלי kli and then you have
to make sure it's not only you take it with the right
but you offer it up on the right with your right hand
as well. And if you want to use a כלי, kli, then
while you have to take it with your right, you could put
it into a כלי kli with your left, and that is so
beyond his just more openness to the use of left, also interesting
about not insisting on the use of a כלי kli for the
second part of the מנחה. Okay, we will stop here.